Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's דף daf is ע"ב. Ayin
Bet. We're well into the סוגיא sugya of העראל He'arel and dealing
with issues of ערלה orlah and the things that a man who
is an ערל arel is not allowed to eat and particularly תרומה
terumah learned out from קרבן פסח Korban Pesach dealing with other aspects
and specifically we were dealing with the fact that בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael were ערלים areilim during the time that they were in the
מדבר midbar as emerges from the story in יהושע. Yehoshua. And the
question is why and the גמרא Gemara says
because they were not able to because it was dangerous because of
health issue because the north wind did not blow. So we continue
a little bit with that אגדתא agadata before we return to הלכה.
halacha. So we pick up about eight lines from the top with
the two dots on ע"ב עמוד א' Ayin Bet amud Alef תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan כל אותן ארבעים שנה kol
osan arba'im shana those whole forty years שהיו ישראל במדבר shehayu Yisrael
bamidbar לא היה יום שלא נשבה בו רוח צפונית. lo haya yom
shelo nashva bo ruach tzephonit. Now until as opposed to what we
just said
yesterday that
the northern wind did not blow all those forty years here it
says there was no day that it did not blow which means
it did blow. However when did it blow? בחצי הלילה bachatzot halayla
exactly at midnight so it did not blow during the day it
did not blow well enough that it should help them in terms
of being healthy enough to be able to do a ברית מילה
bris milah but nevertheless it did blow at least at
midnight שנאמר shene'emar the verse said ויהי בחצי הלילה וה' הכה כל
בכור בארץ מצרים. Vayehi bachatzot halayla v'Hashem hika kol bechor b'eretz Mitzrayim.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי תלמודא Mai talmuda how you learn
it from that verse? הא קמשמע לן Ha kamoshma lan דעת רצון
מילתא היא de'eis ratzon milta hi what you learn is that חצות
chatzot is a time that God
finds is desirous towards us. Of course very funny evidence the fact
that it's a time that all of the Egyptians got killed or
all the firstborn got killed there was a plague but that was
ultimately seen
as redemption of Israel. So therefore there we learn that that's an
עת רצון eis ratzon again quite
interesting because
certainly have said that it's an
עת דין eis din
but no but it's being interpreted as an עת רצון eis ratzon
and therefore even when there was not going to be a רוח
צפונית ruach tzephonit during the day at least there
were some counterpart
to this divine עת רצון eis ratzon there's going to be somehow
expressed
in some way down here on the earth and that's expressed by
the northern wind which by the way has a lot to do
with
תיקון חצות. Tikkun Chatzot. The understanding that even though night is generally
assumed to be an עת דין eis din חצות chatzot is assumed
to be
an עת רצון. eis ratzon. Why don't we do תיקון דאורייתא tikkun
d'Oraita חצות? chatzot?
All right because we're not learning that סוגיא sugya right now. But
all right now aside for two versions by the way though about
תיקון חצות Tikkun Chatzot besides the recent debates about whether how much
of it was impacted by the advent of coffee or not which
I know there's a thesis that it was and then there's a
counter-thesis that says it's bogus but anyway but also they didn't have
alarm clocks so how did they get up at midnight? So I
had one thesis which was no it just meant dark it was
pretty dark out and with no artificial lighting or whatever look it's
so pitch dark out it's חצות chatzot and they said תיקון חצות.
Tikkun Chatzot. That was one version I heard but another actually my
students pointed me to a series of studies that have been done
recently that are articles that came out that said your great-grandparents or
whatever didn't sleep like you sleep which basically they show that if
you take people and you remove all artificial lighting and you put
them into just in natural lit type of condition or whatever and
you take them away from their daily sleep structure and just look
at their natural sleep patterns that they'll fall asleep when it gets
dark and sleep for about four four hours then they'll wake up
and have two hours of wakefulness in the night and then they'll
fall back asleep and that that actually is the most the natural
sleep patterns of the body. So that there's suggestions that that's exactly
what תיקון חצות Tikkun Chatzot was if you naturally woke up in
the middle of the night and there was a period of wakefulness
that was a time to do these סליחות slichot or whatever the
תיקון tikkun and then you would fall back asleep. And that's דוד
המלך David Hamelech that the harp would blow so again רש"י Rashi
says רש"י Rashi quotes here that it was the רוח צפונית ruach
tzephonit that blew at midnight that blew that harp that would wake
up דוד המלך David Hamelech at חצות chatzot that גמרא Gemara in
ברכות. Berachot. So that's exactly connected to this. Yes.
I think the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachot says something about refers
to the time when husbands and wives talk at חצות. chatzot.
Oh that's a nice theory too.
No that's right before the morning
I think.
Is that? I don't know have to re-check up. Okay go double
check. Anyways if anybody's interested I'll try to remember to post a
link to that on our listserve. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna דבר תורה devar Torah back to
הלכה. halacha. דבר תורה Devar Torah משוך אוכל בתרומה. mashoch ochel biterumah.
It's הלכה halacha
biblically speaking a משוך mashoch somebody who has been circumcised but then
reversed the circumcision by I don't exactly know the medical process. procedure,
but there is a medical procedure that you can basically try to
take some skin and stretch it and recreate the ערלה. orlah. Okay,
so that person is technically not an ערל. arel. It doesn't matter
what it looks like, the foreskin has been removed, he's had a
ברית מילה, bris milah, so he can theoretically eat תרומה. trumah. מדבריהם
גזרו עליו מפני שנראה כערל. midivreihem gazru alav mipne shenireh ke'arel.
It's Rabbinic because it looks like an ערל. arel. And it's funny
that they make it because it looks like, like who's looking at
him? But anyway, but you know, it could be confusing here. Now,
of course, the bigger reason might have to be, you know, because
it might be, you know, there could also be sort of like
policy reasons for that, because the question is who is doing this
reversal operation? So let's read a little bit in the גמרא, Gemara,
we'll see, just one minute.
מתיבי: meisiv: משוך צריך שימול. mashoch tzarich sheyimal. We have a ברייתא,
braisa, it says a משוך, mashoch, somebody who has
reversed the, the thing, stretched it so it looks like an ערל,
arel, has to, have to get a
ברית מילה. bris milah. מדרבנן! mi-derabbanan! Fine, it doesn't prove it's biblical,
it's Rabbinic. So the גמרא Gemara says דקא רמי מאי קא רמי
ליה, de-ka-remi mai ka-remi lei, whoa, whoa, what are you thinking? Of
course you could say it's Rabbinic. You know, it doesn't even say
אסור assur in תרומה, trumah, just says צריך. tzarich. צריך tzarich is
not a heavy language, it even sounds very clearly like it is
Rabbinic. Why did you think that was a proof otherwise? So the
גמרא Gemara says הא צריך תני. ha tzarich tani. It says you
need to. It could have said, you know, הרי זה, harei zeh,
you know, ערלה, orlah, could have said a lot more, you know,
very black and white. ערלה, orlah, it could have said a lot
more very black and white. That itself suggests that you, you know,
that it's not a heavy obligation. I mean obviously it's an obligation,
it's דרבנן, derabbanan, but it's not like biblical. So the גמרא Gemara
says דקתני בסיפא. de-ka-tani be-seifa.
He made a mistake because of the end of the ברייתא, braisa,
which made it sound that it was biblical. How did the end
of the ברייתא braisa make it sound that it was biblical? רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, here's the end of the ברייתא, braisa,
לא ימול מפני שסכנה היא לו. lo yimal mipne she-sakana hi lo.
No, it should, it will be a danger. You know, as opposed
to a normal ברית מילה, bris milah, here it's because this whole
thing got stretched or whatever, you try to do a ברית מילה
bris milah on that, like you might turn the person as רש"י
Rashi says into a כרות שפכה, kerus shofcha, you might turn the
person into like, you know, you know, unable to have children, damage
actually his genitals. So the גמרא Gemara says, so he says don't
do it. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, והלא הרבה מלו בימי בן כוזיבא והולידו בנים ובנות. vhalo harbeh
malu bi-ymei Ben Koziva ve-holidu banim u-vanot.
Many have, you know, because, many got, many got a ברית מילה
bris milah in the time of בן כוזיבא, Ben Koziva, and they
had children afterwards.
שנאמר, shene'emar,
I'll get back to that in a minute. המול ימול. himol yimol.
And we see there's an idea to do it again, even if
it didn't take the first time or if it got reversed, because
it says a double language, המול ימול. himol yimol. אפילו מאה פעמים.
afilu me'ah pe'amim.
And the verse says את בריתי הפר et briti heifar that you
have reversed, you have, you have like, violated my covenant. So what
does that mean? Who's violated God's covenant? Not just by passively not
getting a ברית מילה, bris milah, but even worse maybe by actively
reversing it. לרבות את המשוך, lerabbot es hamashoch, even to someone who
has done this and reversed it, that's את בריתי הפר, et briti
heifar, and he has to correct it by doing a ברית מילה.
bris milah. So it's quoting פסוקים. psukim. So that makes it sound
like it's biblical. מאי ואומר? mai ve-omer? What does it mean? Why
do you need the second פסוק? pasuk? So that's going to be
the answer. So what do you mean ואומר? ve-omer? וכי תימא האי
המול ימול לציצין המעכבין, ve-chi teima hai himol yimol le-tzitzin she-me'akvin, the
double language is not to tell you do it a second time
if it was reversed, but tell you you have to even go
back and even if you removed the basic foreskin, if there's little,
little bits of flesh that are still left of it, you have
to, that prevent it from being good, you have to go back
and remove them again and finish the job. המעכבין את המילה, ha-me'akvin
es hamila, so that's what it's coming to tell you. תא שמע:
tashma: את בריתי הפר, et briti heifar, so I'll go quote you
another פסוק. pasuk. לרבות את המשוך. lerabbot es hamashoch. Okay. הוא דסבר,
hu de-savar,
now he assumed that he was proving from this that it's biblical.
מדקנסיב לה הש"ס קרא, mi-de-ka-nessiv leh hashas kra,
since the funny phrase, since the הש"ס. hashas. You know, the הש"ס
hashas means the הש"ס, hashas, the, the Tannaic author is a funny
way because we normally think of הש"ס hashas as גמרא. Gemara. But
the גמרא Gemara refers to הש"ס hashas which is the ששה סדרי,
shisha sidrei, which is the משנה. Mishnah. But anyway, this isn't a
משנה, Mishnah, this is a ברייתא. braisa. But anyway, somehow it's funny
that הש"ס hashas here represents the Tannaic author. Since the Tannaic author
quoted a verse, so דאורייתא, de-oraisa, it means it's biblical. ולאו היא
מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. ve-lav hi mi-derabbanan ve-kra asmachta be-alma. The verse
is only an אסמכתא. asmachta. Okay. So what you do see,
so what's interesting about all of this is you get a hint
to the historical context because it says בימי בן כוזיבא, bi-ymei Ben
Koziva, and it's, you know, it's, I think pretty established, I think
certainly from this, but I think other sources as well, that of
course in the, you know, during that period, and I think in
the Hellenistic period as well since we're coming right around the bend
of Chanukah, in Josephus,
okay, that people, Jews wanted to be like the Greeks. So maybe
in the Hellenistic period because they were attracted to, you know, the
Hellenism and the Greek culture and so on and they wanted to
basically assimilate. And in the Bar Kochba period because of the oppressions,
and they wanted to therefore for different reasons, you know, sometimes because
of the attractions of the outside society, sometimes because of the oppression,
wanted to. to you know give up their Jewish identity or pretend
as you know or make it look as if that they were
not Jewish or that they did not have a ברית מילה brit
mila, *brit milah* or certainly by the Greeks it wasn't just not
being Jewish. It was I think I'm being I think I'm being
anachronistic, but you know in terms of the Hellenism it was that
because the Greeks saw the ברית מילה brit milah *brit milah* as
a disfiguration of the body. And then you know one also wonders
here that the when בן כוזיבא *Ben Kosiba* they went ahead and
they reversed it. Were we talking that it was always a you
know again a you know was it was it forced upon them
you know the to go back and to reverse it or not?
Similar by the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim*. You know I don't know maybe Dov
will fill us in on some of the history.
Dov remembers in Josephus explains the language here of מערים *me'arim* they
were viewable because in the Hellenistic period people went around naked.
Oh people went around naked
in order to play athletics in the גימנסיה *gymnasia*. Right, right and
they were all naked when they played. Right, right, right. It was
a religious ceremony to be involved in that.
Right, right, right. So it so I think that you had that
both in that period and in the time of בר כוכבא *Bar
Kokhba* and again I don't know whether when they reversed it I'm
not remembering I didn't check up on the I didn't check up
on the on the history of it but I think that you
know I think it wasn't also always necessarily free will the fact
that people who who did it were you know all of a
sudden woke up and decided to reverse it. I think it might
have had to do with the fact that there was בר כוכבא
*Bar Kokhba* around or the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim* around.
Anyway but then they reverse the reverse.
That's what I mean. The fact that they reversed the reverse. I'm
sorry, yeah, the fact that they reversed the reverse was not always
necessarily an act of free will. Okay. I'm just trying to take
a look because I remember that there's also a תוספתא Tosefta. *Tosefta*
about this
that a little bit gives historical context
but the תוספתא *Tosefta* might be in שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*. Let me
just take a look quickly.
Yeah I didn't get a chance to check. Alright I'm not seeing
the תוספתא *Tosefta* here it might be in שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*.
Okay anyway so that's the issue about משוך mashoch *mashoch*. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay
מיתיבי meisivei, *meisei* I'll ask you on this claim that a משוך
mashoch, *mashoch* rabbinically has to again get a ברית מילה brit milah,
*brit milah*. מיתיבי
*meisei* I'll ask you on this: טומטום אינו אוכל בתרומה tumtum eino
ochel bitruma. *Tumtum eino ochel betrumah*. נשיו ועבדיו אוכלין *Nashav va'avadav ochlin*.
So a טומטום tumtum *tumtum* somebody whose genitals are covered up and
you don't know if he's man or male or female doesn't eat
תרומה truma? *trumah*. Now why doesn't he eat תרומה truma? *trumah*? It's
not clear. If he's the son he she is the son of
a כהן kohen *kohen* so either way should be able to eat
תרומה truma *trumah*. So the point is because if he is a
he then he has a then he's an ערל arel. *arel* because
since his genitals are covered up then if then he hasn't had
a ברית מילה brit milah, *brit milah* right if he's a man.
So therefore because he might be a male and therefore he'll be
an ערל arel. *arel* he doesn't eat תרומה truma. *trumah*. Now נשיו
ועבדיו אוכלין *nashav va'avadav ochlin* his wives and slaves eat. Now his
slaves of course because whether he's a male or a
female again child of a כהן kohen, *kohen* can eat and the
slaves can eat. But what about his wives? How do you know
how could he be married? Maybe he's a female and maybe he
doesn't have wives right even if he gave money to even if
he gave like כסף קידושין kidushin. *kesef kiddushin* to a woman. So
we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. משוך mashoch, *mashoch*
somebody that has this reversed ונולד כשהוא מהול *venolad keshu maul* or
somebody born when he with already without a foreskin הרי אלו אוכלין
*harei eilu ochlin* they can eat. So נולד כשהוא מהול *nolad keshu
maul* we've discussed before you know about whether that person requires הטפת
דם ברית hatafat dam brit, *hatafat dam brit* or not. Here it's
saying he's not an ערל arel. *arel*. And but משוך mashoch, *mashoch*
also can eat. So that's a proof that not only that it's
not biblically forbidden maybe even proof that it's rabbinically permissible. אנדרוגינוס androgynos
*Androginos* an androgynous who has both male and female genitalia אוכל בתרומה
*ochel betrumah* can eat תרומה truma. *trumah* because presumably he had a
ברית מילה brit milah *brit milah* done on his male you know
done you know done then he can eat תרומה terumah? *trumah* even
though he has both genitalia. Either he's a male or a woman
or some third category but either way he's the child of a
כהן kohen *kohen* and and he's not an ערל arel *arel*. ואינו
אוכל בקדשים *ve'eino ochel bekodshim* but can't eat קדשים kodashim *kodshim* because
we're talking about the קדשי קדשים kodshim. *kodshei kodshim* that are eaten
by the כהנים *kohanim* and the and their sons and only by
male כהנים *kohanim* and therefore he might be a female or some
third category and therefore cannot eat קדשים kodshim, *kodshim*. טומטום tumtum *tumtum*
now going back to טומטום tumtum *tumtum* אינו אוכל לא בתרומה ולא
בקדשים lo bitruma velo bekodashim. *eino ochel lo betrumah velo bekodshim* cannot
eat neither תרומה terumah *trumah* nor קדשים *kodshim* again קדשים *kodshim* also
because might be a female and male who's an ערל arel. *arel*
either way it's obvious can't eat קדשים *kodshim*. Okay קתני מיהת *ktani
mi'at* before we get into worrying about that whole ברייתא beraita *braita*
let's hone on the one line that we taught משוך mashoch, ונולד
כשהוא מהול הרי אלו אוכלין *mashoch venolad keshu maul harei eilu ochlin*
that the משוך meshokh *mashoch* can eat. So תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא
tyuvta deRav Huna tyuvta, *tiyuvta derav huna tiyuvta*. This is a total
contradiction of רב הונא Rav Huna. *Rav Huna*. Why is it a
total contradiction? Because רב הונא *Rav Huna* said he's rabbinically forbidden and
here it sounds like he's totally permissible. Now that's pretty strange because
a minute ago the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was considering either rabbinically forbidden
or biblically forbidden and here according to a ברייתא braita, *braita* it
says it's completely permissible. So רש"י *Rashi* actually suggest has a completely
different גירסא *girsa* of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I don't know if
he rewrites the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* or he actually had a different
גירסא *girsa* but he said one גירסא *girsa* was the way we
have it and it shows it's completely
permissible. So then he actually says this is a proof to רב
הונא, not תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא, it's a proof to רב הונא.
When it says permissible, it means it's at least biblically permissible. Okay,
yeah maybe rabbinically forbidden, but at least it's biblically permissible. Okay. The
רש״י, Rashi, the big רש״י Rashi באין קטנים משוך אוכל, be-ein ktanim
mashuch ochel,
about ten lines before the lines get wide. Okay. So anyway, so
either it's a complete contradiction or it's a total support. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara's continues. קטני מיהא katani miha משוך אוכל.
mashuch ochel. Okay, just אמר מר, amar mar, טומטום אינו אוכל tumtum
eino ochel, בתרומה. A טומטום tumtum, can't eat, but נשיו ועבדיו אוכלים.
nashav ve-avadav ochlim. So
the גמרא Gemara says, but the wives can? נשיו דטומטום מנא ליה?
nashav detumtum mena leh? Where does a טומטום tumtum. get a wife?
אילימא דקידש איתתא, eileima dekideish itata, if he married a woman? דתניא:
detanya: טומטום שקידש, tumtum shekideish, קידושיו קידושין. kidushav kidushin. If a טומטום
tumtum marries a woman, then it's considered a good קידושין. kidushin נתקדש,
nitkadesh, or if he was married by a man, somebody gave the
טומטום, tumtum you know, a ring and wanted to marry this person,
so קידושיו קידושין? kidushav kidushin? It counts, we can, meaning from a
ספק safek we have to be concerned. Maybe he's a man, maybe
she's a woman. So whether he married a woman or whether a
man married him, we say maybe it's a good קידושין with all
the implications, right?
Implications immediately about relatives and all those other types of
things and bringing back the יבמה.
yevama. That's right, exactly. So if that's why we're going to say
that, but wait a minute, אימא דאמרי, eima de-amri, when would we
say something like this? לחומרא, le-chumra, to be strict. Maybe he's the
opposite sex and maybe therefore it's binding and therefore has implications for
relatives and the need for גט get and all other types of
things, right, but ממזרות, mamzerut, exactly. But לקולא מי אמרינן, lekula mi
amrinan, why would we, how could we say it לקולא lekula to
assume he's male and assume that this woman is his wife and
therefore the wife of a כהן kohen, and can eat תרומה? terumah
How could we say that? ספק אישה היא, safek isha hi, she
might be a woman, ואין אישה מקדשת אישה, ve-ein isha mekadeshet isha,
a woman can't marry a woman. So אמר אביי: amar Abaye: כביציו
מבחוץ. kiveitzav mibachutz. Fine,
he's not a total טומטום. tumtum, He's not a טומטום tumtum that
we don't know what he is. He actually, part of this skin
that's covering up his genitals, it's, you know, his testicles have descended
and you can see his testicles. So you know that he's male.
It's just that you're not able to give him a ברית מילה,
brit milah, so he's an ערל. arel Okay, but then it's not
so much more interesting than a normal ערל. arel. Okay, but that's
what אביי Abaye says. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so that's אביי's Abaye
explanation. It's just the case where you ממש mamash do know he's
male. רבא אמר: Rava amar: No, מאי נשיו? mai nashav? What does
it mean his women eat in תרומה? terumah אמו, imo, his mother!
Which by the way shows the interesting word that אישה, isha, of
course, can mean wife or woman. Like some people have suggested that
the name of the tractate of the סדר seder of ש״ס Shas
that we are in, נשים, Nashim, should not be translated as women
but as wives. Interesting, right? Anyway, so רבא Rava says it means
that his mother. אמו פשיטא? imo pshita? Meaning his mother, he is,
his mother is married to a כהן, kohen right, he's the son
of a כהן kohen, or daughter of a כהן, kohen and she
can eat even though you don't know if he's a boy or
girl. So the גמרא Gemara says, of course! The wife of a
כהן kohen and then the כהן, the father died. Okay, but the
wife of the כהן can eat as long as there is some
surviving child. It doesn't matter boy or girl. So of course that
would be obvious that his mother could eat besides it's not פשט.
pshat. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, אי
מה הזרע מוליד ומאכיל, ei ma hazera molid umachil, שאין מוליד אינו
מאכיל, she-ein molid eino machil, maybe only a child that can give
birth, that can bring about a next generation can cause his mother
to
eat, אל בית אביה. el beit aviha. I'm not sure because maybe
there's some sense of continuity.
Yeah, but then you'd say this person ends up being a סריס
saris and the mother can't eat?
All right, it was a הוה אמינא hava amina and the assumption
was that a טומטום tumtum is not able to have children. So
קמשמע לן kamashma lan otherwise. Clearly רבא Rava is not פשט. pshat.
אביי Abaye is also a stretch. Okay, תא שמע. ta shema. No,
תא שמע: ta shema: טומטום tumtum, אינו אוכל, לא בתרומה ולא v'lo?
בקדשים. So a טומטום, tumtum, the end of the ברייתא braita says
a טומטום tumtum can't eat תרומה terumah, and קדשים after the beginning
it already said it couldn't eat תרומה. terumah So בשלמא לאביי, bishlama
le-Abaye, תנא רישא tana reisha ערל ודאי. arel vadai. In the beginning
we talked about a normal, somebody who is a טומטום tumtum but
you knew he was male and you knew he was an ערל.
arel, And that's number one, can't eat תרומה. terumah, And then it
repeats at the end: ותני סיפא vetani seifa ספק ערל, safek arel,
a normal טומטום, tumtum normal טומטום, tumtum a normal טומטום tumtum where
you don't know male or female who is a ספק ערל, safek
arel, even that one can't eat. So there's a nice progression according
to אביי. Abaye. It's an unusual טומטום tumtum who is a ודאי
ערל, vadai arel, and then the end is a normal טומטום tumtum
who is a ספק ערל safek arel and even that one can't
eat. אלא לרבא, ela le-Rava, but רבא Rava who said the רישא
reisha was according, a normal טומטום tumtum and couldn't eat even though
it was a ספק ערל. safek arel. So טומטום דסיפא למה לי?
tumtum deseifa lama li? Why did it have to repeat the idea
of טומטום tumtum. in the end? No, מאי טומטום ערל? mai tumtum
arel? No, when in the end it says that a טומטום tumtum
can't eat it means somebody who is a definite ערל arel can't
eat. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay that doesn't help the issue.
השתא ספק ערל לא אכיל, hashta safek arel lo achil, the first
it said a טומטום tumtum and a normal טומטום tumtum and it
said he
couldn't eat.
Here's why it repeats טומטום. tumtum. It's explaining to you why it
first said that a טומטום tumtum, was forbidden. מה טעם טומטום אינו
אוכל בתרומה, mah ta'am tumtum eino ochel biterumah,
why did we say initially, says the ברייתא, braita, that a טומטום
tumtum can't eat תרומה? terumah, מפני שספק ערל הוא, mipnei shesafek arel
hu, because he might be a male and therefore he's an ערל.
arel. וערל אינו אוכל לא בתרומה ולא בקדשים, ve'arel eino ochel lo
biterumah velo bekodshim, and somebody who's an ערל arel can't eat תרומה
terumah and קדשים. So when it says again טומטום tumtum. doesn't eat
תרומה terumah. and קדשים, it means it's explaining to you because he
might be an ערל. arel Of course, again, very funny, then say
ערל, arel don't say טומטום. tumtum Okay, anyway, two interesting ways of
explaining that ברייתא braita about the טומטום, tumtum but we still have
this question about whether a משוך meshokh, eats תרומה terumah? biblically does
not eat תרומה, terumah whether the issue is biblical or rabbinic.
Yes, does this ברייתא, baraita this statement about a טומטום tumtum שקידש
shekidesh או נתקדש o nitkadesh או קדושה חלה o kedushah chala help
with applications today with transgender?
So, yeah, so I mean, very
powerful statement.
Yeah, no, but טומטום. tumtum So טומטום tumtum is less interesting.
Okay, the short answer is that טומטום tumtum is less interesting because
טומטום is a case of a ספק. safek. And אנדרוגינוס androgynos tends
to be more interesting because אנדרוגינוס androgynos suggests that there's in addition
to the whole transgender thing, there's this intersex thing, which is not
having a binary division of the sexes and allowing for the possibility
that somebody's neither male nor female. So that people find the whole
idea of אנדרוגינוס androgynos, and the גמרא's Gemara consideration that it might
be, or the תנאי Tannaic possibility that it might be בריה בפני
עצמה, biryah bifnei atzmah, neither male nor female, that we might recognize
the third category, that people find very interesting for the intersex issue.
As far as the transgender issue, less so, because the טומטום is
just a question what's it going to tell you he has, and
which gets down really to the question of the assumption of the
גמרא Gemara that sex is determined by genitalia. Yeah, and, but then
becomes the issue. Well, and a lot of people that are transgender
are not transsexual, and don't even have an operation to change their
genitalia, so it doesn't, so that's to the degree that there's some
conversation about will it change a person's הלכה halakhic status, it's only
like if there's been an operation and the actual genitalia have changed.
And even there, the overwhelmingly dominant position is that it's defined by
what somebody is when they're born. The interesting question that remains, or
whatever, anyway, although there's still obviously conversation going on about that. The
other question that remains is if somebody is born with, sometimes as
an infant is born with either as an אנדרוגינוס, androgynos like, somehow,
or if not technically an אנדרוגינוס androgynos? where the doctors have to
determine which sex the baby's going to be through some type of
an operation and so on. And that's where there's actually an indeterminate
status at birth. So if there's an indeterminate status at birth to
say then through some type of an operation we could actually fix
the הלכה halakhic status, that there's maybe more basis to say. When
somebody has a very defined status at birth and then changes it
later in life, that becomes more complicated הלכה. halakhically. Okay, that was
a quick שיעור shiur on transgender, thank you, or transsexual. Moving on.
אמר... Amar... where were we? לימא כתנאי. Leima ketannai. Why, you didn't
think that what we're doing is enough הלכה למעשה, halakha lema'aseh, you
had to bring in that other stuff? All right, anyway, okay, לימא
כתנאי. leima ketannai. Maybe this issue about a משוך, mashuch whether it's
biblical or rabbinic that he can't eat, is a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. Because we said משוך, meshoch בנו של קרומה beno shel kerumah
is a debate whether this is in this תוספתא. וגר שנתגייר כשהוא
מהול, v'ger shenitgayer keshehu mahul, and a convert who was already at
a ברית מילה brit milah before and then converted, right? All these
are people that have to do a ברית מילה, brit milah but
not the classic ברית מילה, brit milah, right? Maybe a הטפת דם
ברית, maybe a ברית מילה brit milah because he's a משוך, maybe
as we'll see, וקטן שעבר זמנו, vekatan she'avar zemano, or even not
on day eight, so which obviously is the biblically obligated ברית מילה,
brit milah but it's just not on the exact normal way on
day eight. ושאר כל הנימולים, veshaar kol hanimmolim, and anybody else who
has to get a ברית מילה brit milah? that's not a classic
case. לאתויי, lasuyei, what would that include? מי שיש לו שתי ערלות,
mi sheyesh lo shtei arlot, like if somebody actually had a double
foreskin, I assume that's the condition. All these people אינם נימולים אלא
ביום. einam nimolin ela bayom. It has to be in the day.
Just because it's not like a classic case, they still have to
do it in the day. And the point being also a lot
of these people won't be doing it on day eight. Somebody who
converts, a משוך, these are people who are doing it as adults,
right? So they're not doing it on day eight. So the basic
point is even though it's not on day eight—and this is a
debate להלכה—if lehalakha a ברית מילה brit milah is later than day
eight, is the requirement of day only for day eight, or does
it continue no matter what day you do it on? So this
ברייתא braita says. Wait, yeah, so let's take a look. So this
ברייתא braita, says that regardless of the day, and regardless of whether
it's a classic case or not, or even if it's not a
classic case, even if it's not on day eight, it has to
be in the day. רבי אלעזר בר שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar bar
Shimon omer, רבי אלעזר בר שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon says no,
בזמנו אינו נימול אלא ביום. bizmano eno nimol ela bayom. If you're
doing it on day eight and a classic ברית מילה, brit milah
it's in the day. שלא בזמנו נימול ביום ובלילה. shelo bizmano nimol
bayom ubalayla. שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano can be even at night. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai lav behaka mifligi?
Let's say this is the debate. דמר סבר משוך דאורייתא, demar savar
meshokh de-Oraita, one holds משוך is דאורייתא, de-Oraita, and therefore presumably if
it's דאורייתא, de-Oraita, it has to be like the classic case and
it has to be daytime. ומר סבר משוך דרבנן, umar savar meshokh
de-Rabbanan, and the other holds that it's דרבנן de-Rabbanan and could be
even night. Of course that doesn't make sense as the גמרא Gemara
immediately says because its list clearly includes some biblical cases. גמרא Gemara
says, ותסברא, v'tisbara, does that make sense that the issue of day
or night is an issue of דאורייתא de-Oraita or דרבנן? de-Rabbanan? קטן
שעבר זמנו, katan she-avar zamano, if it's not day eight for this
infant, מי איכא למאן דאמר דרבנן? mi ika leman d'amar de-Rabbanan? Nobody
would say it's דרבנן, de-Rabbanan, right? So clearly it's not about biblical
or Rabbinic the issue of day eight. אלא דכולי עלמא משוך דרבנן.
ela dekuly alma meshokh de-Rabbanan. Let's assume like we've been saying all
along that the need for a ברית מילה Brit Milah, after this
reversal surgery, after this person is a משוך, that's only a דרבנן
de-Rabbanan need. Fine. Number one. וקטן שעבר זמנו דאורייתא, vekatan she-avar zamano
de-Oraita, on the other hand, another one on this list, the infant
after day eight is biblical. So the list contains both clearly דרבנן
de-Rabbanan obligations and דאורייתא de-Oraita obligations. So the issue has nothing to
do with biblical or Rabbinic. The issue has to do with what's
the הלכה halacha after day eight. Okay. והכא בהא קמיפלגי, vehacha behai
kemifligi, here's the debate. מר סבר דרשינן וביום, mar savar darshinan ubayom,
it says ביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו. bayom hashmini yimol basar orlato.
So the extra vav, וביום, ubayom, to tell you even if it's
not day eight, it has to be יום, yom, it has to
be daytime. ומר סבר לא דרשינן, umar savar lo darshinan, and the
other says we don't read וביום. ubayom. Okay, so in the end
it's just a question of what do you do with that extra
vav. Or if you don't want to make it like as technical
of a point, you would say the תורה Torah says ביום השמיני.
bayom hashmini. So what do we assume happens after day eight? Is
the תורה Torah underscoring the idea of יום yom only for when
it starts? It starts day eight, not the night before? Or is
there a general demand of ביום? bayom? Okay, and that's the debate.
כי הא דיתיב רבי יוחנן וקא דרש, ki ha deyativ Rabbi Yochanan
veka darash, Rabbi Yochanan was sitting and he was expounding. נותר בזמנו
אינו נשרף אלא ביום. nosar bizmano eno nisraf ela bayom. נותר nosar
is something that has to be burnt. It says והנותר ביום השלישי
באש ישרף, vehanotar bayom hashlishi baesh yisaref, the meat that's leftover from
the sacrifices on day three. So he says ביום השלישי, bayom hashlishi,
day three. That's if you did it on day three, it has
to be ביום. bayom. שלא בזמנו נשרף ביום ובלילה. shelo bizmano nisraf
bayom ubalayla. So day three is when it starts. But after the
beginning, after the obligation starts, it continues into the night and it
goes for following nights, it's not limited to day. Okay, that would
be a parallel to say ברית מילה Brit Milah, starts day eight
but afterwards can be done in the night, that's like רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. That's what he was saying by נותר. nosar. Okay. התיבו
רבי אלעזר לרבי יוחנן, hetivu Rabbi Elazar le-Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar asked רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אין לי אלא נימול לשמיני
שאינו נימול אלא ביום. en li ela nimol lishmini she'eno nimol ela
bayom. I only know that day eight to only be נימול nimol
in the day. מניין לרבות לתשעה לעשרה לאחד עשר ולשנים עשר? minayin
lerabot letisha leasara leachad asar velishnem asar? How do I know even
if it's on day 9, 10, 11, and 12, that it could
only be in the daytime for ברית מילה? Brit Milah תלמוד לומר
וביום, talmud lomar ubayom, the extra vav tells you that even if
it's later, it's not it starts on day eight and then continues
straight. Even on a later date, it's only the daytime. Just one
moment mention about why it says 9, 10, 11, and 12, because
sort of like מגילה נקראת, Megilla Nikret, okay, because you can get
in classic situations, even if you're not doing anything wrong and the
baby is healthy, 9, 10, 11, and 12. Right. So nine is
that the baby is born on ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. So therefore,
he's born on ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, you can't do it Friday,
you can't do it שבת. Shabbat So בין השמשות, bein hashmashot, right,
I'm sorry, ערב שבת בין השמשות. erev Shabbat bein hashmashot. So you
wind up doing it like on Sunday. So that is like that's
day nine, even if you assume that I mean it depends on
where you start counting from. Friday, if you start from Friday, it's
day ten. No, that is day ten. Oh no, a normal בין
השמשות, bein hashmashot, right, a normal בין השמשות bein hashmashot is day
nine. A baby is born between Sunday and Monday. So when are
you going to do it? So you have to assume the later,
Monday, and then you do it the next Monday, but that's day
nine from the possibility of Sunday. If it was שבת, then you
got to push it off another day, it's day ten. If it's
שבת followed by a day יום טוב Yom Tov or two days
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, day 11 or day 12. Okay. So anyway,
so he says, look, there we already say that you have to
do it in the day even if it's later. דאפילו מאן דלא
דריש וביום, deafillu man d'lo darash ubayom, and even the opinion that
would disagree with that, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, and wouldn't find the
וביום ubayom and say a ברית מילה Brit Milah, that's שלא בזמנו
shelo bizmano could be at night, וו"ה דריש, vav he darish, the
וו"ה vav he because it says והנותר. vehanotar. So by ברית מילה
anyway it says the day when it's late. And even though there's
an opinion that disagrees, that's just because there's one vav, וביום. ubayom.
But here it says והנותר, vehanotar, the וו"ה vav he tells you
that even if it's... It's not the immediately after, it's come to
tell you that there's extra cases where it's still going to remain
only ביום bayom even if it's not בזמנו. bizmano. Okay, so אישתיק,
Ishtik, he was silent, he didn't respond, made a good point, probably
knows there has to be ביום bayom as well. בתר דנפיק, Batar
de-nafik, after רב אלעזר Rav Elazar went out, אמר ליה רב יוחנן
לריש לקיש, Amar leih Rav Yochanan le-Resh Lakish, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
said to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, ראיתי לבן פדת, Ra'iti le-Ben Pdat,
I saw בן פדת, Ben Pdat, that's רב אלעזר בן פדת, Rav
Elazar Ben Pdat, who's the אמורא, Amora, not to be confused with
the תנא, Tanna, רב אלעזר בן שמוע. Rav Elazar Ben Shammua. שיושב
ודורש כמשה מפי הגבורה. She-yoshev ve-doresh ke-Moshe mi-pi ha-Gevurah. He's sitting and
expounding like משה Moshe straight from God, because he's quoting these פסוקים
psukim and he's saying what it means, right, וביום השמיני u-ba-yom ha-shemini
on the eighth and so on. So it's interesting because רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan was the one who was sitting and expounding verses. What's
he offended by, right? It's an interesting question, which is, do only
the תנאים Tannaim do מדרשי הלכה, midreshei Halacha, or can the אמוראים
Amoraim also do מדרשי הלכה? midreshei Halacha? Right, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
was doing מדרש הלכה, midrash Halacha, right? He was דרשנ'ינג darshaning the
פסוקים psukim about נותר. notar. And רב אלעזר Rav Elazar came back
and he said, no, look at how we דרשן darshan it by
ברית מילה, you have to דרשן darshan it differently here. So maybe
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan felt that רב אלעזר Rav Elazar was doing
a better job דרשנ'ינג darshaning it than him. You know, it's not
clear if it was a criticism or like an appreciation, right? So
it's not exactly clear, right, and you know, but רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan was doing the same thing. But oh, רב אלעזר Rav Elazar
was doing it מפי הגבורה, mi-pi ha-Gevurah, either it means like, you
know, he speaks with a voice of authority, did it better than
me, or he's being critical, he's doing it with too much sense
of authority. Anyway, so let's take a look. Now so, אמר ליה
ריש לקיש, Amar leih Resh Lakish, so ריש לקיש Resh Lakish might
be because the way he quoted the פסוקים psukim from ברית מילה,
he just said, אמר רב אלעזר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Elazar Rav
Yochanan, אין לי אלא נימול לשמיני. ein li ela nimol li-shmini. He
didn't say תניא, tanya, he just said אין לי אלא נימול לשמיני,
ein li ela nimol li-shmini, like maybe he was saying that דרשה
drasha about ברית מילה on his own authority or something. And that
seems to be what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says back to him.
אמר ליה ריש לקיש, Amar leih Resh Lakish, so ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish said that back to רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, דידיה? Dideih? You
think he got that whole thing about that דרשה drasha on his
own? No, מתניתין היא. Matnitin hi. It's a ברייתא braita. he was
quoting you. He wasn't quoting it like on his own authority, this
דרשה drasha by ברית מילה, he was quoting you a ברייתא, braita
even though he didn't say תניא, tanya, he just said it, but
it was a ברייתא. braisa So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan said back
to him, היכא תנא ליה? Heicha tana leih? So where did he
learn this ברייתא Braisa from? So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said back
to him, בתורת כהנים, Be-Toras Kohanim, he got it from the ספרא.
Sifra. So נפק, nafik, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan went out, תנייה בתלתא
יומי, tanyah be-tlata yomei, he learned תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim in three
days, וסברה בתלתא ירחי, ve-savrah be-tlata yarchei, then he spent the next
three months figuring it out or like analyzing it. Okay, first he
memorized and he has, which is fascinating, what does that mean? Until
that moment רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan had never learned תורת כהנים? Toras
Kohanim? Maybe he didn't appreciate it, he didn't learn it as well
as he should've. Anyway, quite fascinating little exchange there. Yeah, רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan and his חברותא. chavruta. What? Yeah, I don't know what
was going on there. He read it so thorough, we can't learn
it that quickly. All right, anyway. Okay, so anyway, okay, אמר רב
אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar, so fine. Anyway what you see there is
that was an interesting suggestion that maybe from that issue of after
day eight, is it day or night, is the question of whether
it's דאורייתא de-oraita or דרבנן, de-rabbanan, but the גמרא Gemara says no,
no, no, no, clearly it's דאורייתא. de-oraita. I mean clearly that list
contains דאורייתא'ס de-oraita's like an infant after day eight and דרבנן'ס, de-rabbanan's,
the משוך cases are דרבנן. de-rabbanan. And nevertheless, there's a general question,
when it's not day eight itself, does it have to remain during
the day or night? Okay, yes. Is תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim written
down at that point? So excellent question. So the general assumption was,
the general assumption was not, was that any writing of any תורה
שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh happened like in the Geonic period. However,
about, I don't know, 20 years ago, שלמה נאה Shlomo Naeh came
out with this brilliant article of which picked a topic which you
like seems like the most deathly dull topic you could ever imagine,
which was the the different divisions of תורת כהנים, Toras Kohanim, because
if you've ever tried to find something in the ספרא, Sifra, it's
got crazy divisions, like one division by פרקים, prakim, one by פרשה'ס,
parsha's, and they don't they're like they're completely they're different divisions laid
upon one another, it doesn't make any sense. So he went and
he tried to uncover like where how that all sort of worked
out. And he found that however those divisions worked out and however
those different systems worked out, they always divided it so that the
sections were of a certain were within a certain range of length.
And he said, and that actually corresponds to in the like in
the in the Greek and Roman period, the acceptable size of scrolls.
Because if you think remember cassette tapes? We had cassette tapes which
were 60 to 90 minutes, maybe 120, but you don't want it
to be too small because then you need too many cassette tapes.
You don't want it to be too long because then you have
to do too much winding. Well, the same was true with a
scroll, right? It's not random access, you gotta do a lot of
scrolling. So there was like there was there was an accepted size,
an appropriate size of scrolls, a range. And he saw that all
the different divisions of תורת כהנים, Toras Kohanim, and some of them
didn't even make sense thematically, but fit in within this range. So
his his argument was was that that he thinks it's the earliest
part of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh that was written down.
And because it goes to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and obviously
you know, the whole בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash sort of dominance preceded
the Tannaitic sort of dominance. Anyway, quite fascinating. So he thinks that,
so that's his argument. It's a quite, quite fascinating argument. So scholars
debate whether they agree with his conclusions, but it was still a
brilliant article. Anyway, moving on. You guys are pulling me in all
these directions, you're not interested enough in issues of משוך or whatever.
Anyway, moving on. All right, so but I notice how I'm responding
to. All right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
אמר רבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Elazar. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said,
ערל שהזה הזאתו כשרה. arel shehizah hazaso kesherah. You know, we're going
through different things an ערל arel may or may not be okay
in doing. I mean, eating תרומה terumah was the beginning, you know,
then an earlier discussion was whether he can receive הזאה hazaah and
become טהור tahor while he's an ערל. arel Now we're asking whether
he can be the one to administer the הזאה. hazaah. Can he
be the one to sprinkle the ashes? So he says, רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar says he can. Is there a reason to think that
he? Well, let's take a look. מי הוי מטבול יום? mi havei
mi-t'vul yom? He's no worse than a טבול יום. tvul yom. Like
טבול יום tvul yom is the classic case where they did it
in order להוציא מלבן של צדוקים, lehotzi milibon shel tzedukim, you know,
to prove that the צדוקים, tzedukim, you know, who were who you
know wanted to say that the כהן had to be like super
טהור. tahor. So what the חכמים chachamim did is they ensured to
use somebody who had gone to the מקוה mikvah that day and
was not totally טהור, tahor, it had not yet been nightfall, to
show that the צדוקים tzedukim were wrong. So a טבול יום tvul
yom who'd been to the מקוה mikvah that day, but still there's
some remnant of טומאה tumah until nightfall, he can do הזאה, hazaah,
שאף על פי שאסור בתרומה, she'af al pi she'asur biterumah, even though
he can't eat תרומה, terumah, כשר בפרה, kasher beparah, he can do
the עבודה avodah of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So therefore this
ערל arel the same, he can't eat תרומה, but he could do
the עבודה. avodah. גמרא Gemara says no, what type of comparison is
that? מה לטבול יום שכן מותר במעשר, mah litvul yom sheken mutar
bemaaser, a טבול יום tvul yom can eat מעשר, maaser, and we're
going to discuss tomorrow that an ערל arel might not be allowed
to eat מעשר. maaser. So it's not clear that an ערל arel
is better than a טבול יום. tvul yom. גמרא Gemara says one
minute no, אטו אכילה קאמינא, atu anachilah kamina, who said we're talking
about eating? Eating, you're right, an ערל arel might be worse than
a טבול יום tvul yom in terms of eating, but eating is
not what you're doing when you're doing the עבודה avodah of a
פרה, parah, it's unrelated, the question of eating. אנא לנגיעה קאמינא, ana
lenegiah kamina, the relevant issue is the ability to touch, to handle
things. So now let's look at it, ואין זה קל וחומר. ve'in
zeh kal vachomer. ומה טבול יום שאסור בנגיעה בתרומה, u'mah tvul yom
she'asur binegiah biterumah, טבול יום tvul yom isn't even allowed to handle
תרומה because he's טמא, tamei, מותר בפרה, mutar beparah, can do the
עבודה avodah of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. ערל arel, who is
not טמא, tamei, שמותר בנגיעה, shemutar binegiah, he can handle תרומה. So
in terms of handling things an ערל arel. is better. אין דין
שמותר בפרה, ain din shemutar beparah, how much more so should he
be allowed to do the עבודה avodah of the פרה אדומה? parah
adumah? Good argument. תניא נמי הכי, tanyi nami hachi, it taught similarly,
ערל שהזה הזאתו כשרה, arel shehizah hazaso kesherah, an ערל arel who
did the הזאה hazaah it's valid. ומעשה היה והכשירו חכמים הזאתו, u'maaseh
hayah vehichshiru chachamim hazaso, and actually this was acted on, it's not
just a theoretical ruling, he did it and they said it was
okay. מיתיבי, they asked on this, טומטום שקידש קידושיו פסול. tumtum shekidesh
kiddushav pasul. So this is not the טומטום that was being מקדש
mekadesh before when he was marrying a woman. Here it is קידוש
kiddush of the מקדש mekadesh the אפר efer of the פרה אדומה.
parah adumah. Okay, so this is the mixing of the ashes of
the פרה אדומה parah adumah with water. So it's invalid, מפני שספק
ערל, mipnei shesafek arel, ערל פסול לקדש. arel pasul lekadesh. So this
is an explicit ברייתא Braisa that says that an ערל arel is
not able to do the עבודה. avodah. Well we'll see, but it
assumes that an ערל arel is not able to do the עבודה
avodah explicitly against you. Not only now, how about an אנדרוגינוס? androgynos
אנדרוגינוס שקידש קידושיו כשר. androgynos shekidesh kiddushav kasher. So there, so the
problem with the טומטום is he might be an ערל, arel but
an אנדרוגינוס androgynos who might be a woman, that's not a problem,
that's okay.
Women to do it, but not an ערל.
arel. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, saying if there's a problem
with קידוש kiddush there's also be a problem with הזאה? hazaah? Yeah,
assuming it's the same, it could theoretically distinguish, but it's assuming it's
the same. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, אף אנדרוגינוס שקידש קידושיו
פסולין. af androgynos shekidesh kiddushav psulin. No, even an אנדרוגינוס is no
good. מפני שספק אשה היא, mipnei shesafek ishah hi, he might be
a woman, ואשה פסולה מלקדש, ve'ishah psulah melekadesh, and a woman is
invalid. So here you have the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma whether a woman could do the
could do the process of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. We'll bracket
that for now. But clearly an ערל arel cannot. תניא, taniya, ערל
וספק ערל פסול מלקדש. arel vesafek arel pasul melekadesh. It's clear that
a definite and even a doubtful ערל arel cannot do the עבודה
avodah of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So how that's exactly against
what you said. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, האי תנא תנא
דבי רבי עקיבא הוא. hai tanna tanna devei Rabbi Akiva hu. This
תנא tanna who says an ערל arel is invalid is of the
school of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דמרבי ליה לערל כטמא. demarbei leh
le'arel ketamei. He treats, if you remember at the beginning of this
פרק, perek, where do you know that an ערל arel can't eat
תרומה? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learned it out from it said what
was the פסוק? pasuk? Something איש איש, ish ish, right? לרבות את
הערל, lerabos es ha'arel, right? איש איש, ish ish, a פסוק pasuk
talking about טמאים, tmei'im, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said the double איש
איש ish ish includes the ערל. arel So if that's the case
we thought that he was doing it for תרומה purposes, it was
included in a quasi טמא tamei category for תרומה purposes. Here the
גמרא Gemara is making a much bolder statement that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva would in all areas treat an ערל arel like a טמא.
tamei. Okay, that's a pretty harsh statement. Now presumably it wouldn't mean
that an ערל arel couldn't touch תרומה, wouldn't transfer, but in terms
of like personal status when a טמא tamei person is excluded, not
just that he transfers טומאה, tumah, an ערל arel would also be
excluded. Okay, so that's why he would be excluded. Near the same
way a טמא tamei just in terms of his personal status is
excluded. So that's a very important distinction. Right. That's- yeah, that would
only be a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position, but that's really making
a very strong categorical statement of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Let's see
what the גמרא does with this. Yes. They're making a distinction between
sanctifying and the sprinkling? No, so that's what Michael asked. They could
have, but they're actually not making a distinction. They're assuming it's the
same. So whoever can't mix the waters also can't sprinkle the waters.
That's the גמרא's assumption. Okay, in theory it could distinguish, but it's
assuming it's the same. So the גמרא says like this: So any
so דתניא d'tanya רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר omer איש איש ish
ish ולרבות את הערל. ul'rabot et ha'arel. And maybe again, not to
transfer טומאה, tumah, but in terms of personal status, maybe he sees
an ערל arel as like a טמא tamei for all things. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so are we really going to accept that this
is now the position of רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? הוי יתיבנא קמיה
דרב יוסף וקשיא לי. Hevei yasivina kamei d'Rav Yosef v'kashyei li. לא
אישתמי תנא וליתני Lo ishtami tanna v'lisnei הערל והטמא ha'arel v'hatamei ולימא
רבי עקיבא היא. v'leima Rabbi Akiva hi. You know, why is it,
it's a hard idiomatic expression to translate, but it basically means like
if this were true, we would have seen it somewhere. How could
it be, how could it not occur here? If there was a
position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that an ערל arel was like
fully like a טמא, tamei, then somewhere in ש"ס Shas we would
have found some statement that said הערל והטמא ha'arel v'hatamei can't do
something and a claim that it was רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. If
there was a position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that an ערל
arel was a טמא, tamei, we would have had heard other echoes
of this. Okay, that we would have treated him like a טמא
tamei and we don't. We always treat him as a distinct category.
So we never had a תנא tanna that said, wouldn't have escaped
that there would have been a תנא tanna that said הערל והטמא
ha'arel v'hatamei and then we would have said that was רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Okay, the גמרא says ולא? Maybe there is an echo
of this. והקתני v'haktani we have a משנה mishna that says הערל
והטמא פטורים מן הראייה. ha'arel v'hatamei paturim min ha're'iyah. Like the ערל
arel and טמא tamei can't do עולת ראייה. olot re'iyah. Why can't
an ערל arel do עליה לרגל? aliya l'regel? Presumably it's because it's
in the same category as the טמא tamei who can't be in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Maybe now think about the implication of
this. So an ערל arel wouldn't be allowed- anyway there's a question
about the ערל arel in בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Anyway. So so
it says that presumably that's why. But it says no, חוץ משום
דמאיס. hutz mishum d'mais. That's just because it's like unseemly for somebody
who's an ערל arel to be in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
but it's not because he's in the category of a טמא. tamei.
Of course, it sort of takes the sting out of רבא's Rava
argument because here you have something that actually says הערל והטמא ha'arel
v'hatamei and there's no obvious reason why ערל arel not and it
might very well be because of an assumption that ערל arel is
like טמא. tamei. So we have a very interesting suggestion because I
mean this is the פרק perek of ערל arel. to think that
there's a position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that is a general
position that in terms of personal status, ערל Arel is treated like
טמא. tamei. So maybe that's why- רבא's Rava objection aside- maybe that's
why he cannot do the thing for the הזאה. hazah. So that's
so that's one answer. Okay, so the גמרא goes on and says
ואזדו לטעמייהו. v'azdu l'taimeihu. Now they go according to their reasoning, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן. Rabbanan. So we really don't have
another answer by the way about here the fact that it says
an ערל Arel is invalid and we said an ערל Arel is
valid. So far the only answer we've had that רבא Rava wasn't
happy with was that it was רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, but
that's so far the only answer we had about whether an ערל
can or cannot. But now we're going to look at the debate
of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda around
this issue about whether a woman can do it. Okay, ואזדו לטעמייהו
v'azdu l'taimeihu דתניא d'tanya תנא ברייתא tana baraita הכל כשירים לקדש, hakol
keshairin lekadesh, anybody could do the mixing of the water and the
אפר efer of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן,
hutz me'cheresh shoteh v'katan, and presumably ערל. רבי יהודה מכשיר בקטן ופוסל
באשה. Rabbi Yehuda machshir b'katan u'posel b'ishah. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says the קטן katan is okay but an אשה ishah is no
good. Okay, so so there you see they're following their debate of
whether an אשה ishah is good or not. Okay, ובאנדרוגינוס מאי טעמא?
u've'androgynos mai taimei? Or באשה ובאנדרוגינוס b'ishah u've'androgynos because he might be
an אשה. ishah. Okay, so here's a debate about קטן katan versus
אשה. ishah. מאי טעמא דרבנן, Mai taimei d'Rabbanan, why did the רבנן
Rabbanan say קטן katan no and אשה ishah yes? דכתיב ולקחו לטמא
מעפר שרפת החטאת, Dichsiv v'lakhu latamei me'afar sereifat hachatat, they shall take
for the טמא tamei person from the ashes and put in water.
Or put water in it. הנך דפסלי באסיפה פסולים בקידוש, Hanakh d'pasli
b'asifah psulin b'kiddush, because it combines ולקחו v'lakhu to to the earlier
פסוק pasuk where it says what's the פסוק? pasuk? ואסף איש טהור.
v'asaf ish tahor. So there it says ואסף איש טהור, v'asaf ish
tahor, so טהור tahor first of all you have to be טהור,
tahor, but it also says איש. ish. So איש ish might be
excluding woman, but the חכמים hakhamim assume no, איש ish excludes a
קטן. katan. Okay? So the combination of ואסף v'asaf and then and
then ולקחו, v'lakhu, sort of the juxtaposition of the verbs says it's
the same person same type of people are good for A are
good for B. Okay, so where were we? הנך דפסלי באסיפה Hanakh
d'pasli b'asifah like a minor, פסולים בקידוש psulin b'kiddush for the קידוש
kiddush and the same way a minor's excluded, somebody who's not a
בר דעת bar da'at like חרש ושוטה heresh v'shoteh are excluded. That's
what the רבנן Rabbanan say. הנך דכשירים באסיפה Hanakh d'kesheirin b'asifah and
somebody who's כשיר, kasher, כשירים בקידוש kesheirin b'kiddush can do the קידוש.
kiddush. Now how an אשה ishah is כשירה באסיפה? kasher b'asifah? How
do you know an אשה ishah is כשירה? kasher? Yeah, now how
do you know an אשה ishah is כשירה באסיפה? kasher b'asifah? It
says איש, ish, so we learn something from somehow from the word
הטהור. ha'tahor. is coming to include a woman. So you just have
to accept that, that elsewhere there's a דרשה Drashah that you need
a adult of sound mind to do the אסיפה Asifah but but
a woman is included. So the rabbis say, so whatever is true
by the אסיפה Asifah is true by the mixing with the water,
the collecting of the ashes. So the same so same status and
therefore it can be any adult, man or woman, but it cannot
be a minor. That's what the rabbis say. רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehudah,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah says, אמר לך Amar lach he'll say to
you, אם כן Im kein if so, נימא קרא Neima kra let
the verse say ולקח V'lakach why doesn't it just use the same
singular? It says it says ואסף, V'asaf, let it say ולקח. V'lakach.
מאי ולקחו? Mai v'laku? Why is it plural? דאפילו הנך דפסולים התם
כשרין הכא. D'afilu hanakh d'psulim hatam ksherin hacha. It's a bigger category
here even people that are invalid there, like a minor, are valid
here. אי הכי Ei hachi אשה נמי? Ishah nami? So if that's
true, let it also be a woman because a woman is even
valid for the gathering of the ashes. So נמי? Nami? ונתן ולא
ונתנה. V'nasan v'lo v'nasnah. No, because he actually says it says ונתן
עליו מים חיים אל כלי, V'nasan alav mayim chayim el keli, so
ונתן ולא ונתנה. V'nasan v'lo v'nasnah. Okay, so that actually somehow that
because it didn't continue in the plural and went to the singular
and the him in the
singular is somehow understood to exclude women. ורבנן, V'rabanan, the rabbis would
say back, אי כתב ולקח ונתן, Ei ksas v'lakach v'nasan, had it
said ולקח ונתן V'lakach v'nasan הוה אמינא Havah amina שקיל חד ויהיב
חד, Shakil chad
v'yahiv chad, that here's why it says ולקחו, V'lakchu, not to tell
you it's different, but to tell you you don't need just one
person doing it or maybe you don't need the same person doing
it. כתב רחמנא ולקחו, Ksas rachmana v'lakchu, it says ולקחו V'lakchu to
tell you you could have more people doing it and different people
doing it. ואי כתב רחמנא ולקחו ונתנו V'ei ksas rachmana v'lakchu v'nasnu
הוה אמינא Havah amina דשקלי תרי ויהבי תרי, D'shakli srei v'yahvi srei,
you need two people doing the whole thing. כתב רחמנא ולקחו ונתן
Ksas rachmana v'lakchu v'nasan דאפילו שקלו תרי ויהיב חד. D'afilu shaklu srei
v'yahiv chad. Fine. So however you work it out though, we have
the rabbis that are emphasizing that it can't—it has to be an
adult of of you know sound mind but man or woman and
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah saying it doesn't have to be an adult
but it does have to be a man. And let's just read
one more פסוק Pasuk here at the very top. והזה הטהור על
הטמא, V'hizah hatahor al hatamei, the pure person shall sprinkle on the
tamei. טהור מכלל שהוא טמא. Tahor miklal shehu tamei. I love that.
You know, that's just such a perfect distillation of like rabbinic דרשות.
Drashot. It says טהור Tahor which means he's טמא, Tamei, okay? Which
means somehow he had been טמא Tamei and he went through a
טהרה Taharah process, but the טהרה Taharah process somehow is not a
hundred percent complete. And that's from there we learn out that the
idea of a טבול יום Tvul yom can do the הזיה. Hazayah.
למימרא טבול יום שכשר בפרה. L'meimra tvul yom shekasher b'parah. And from
there you learn that a טבול יום Tvul yom can do the
פרה אדומה Parah adumah and from that we wanted to say can
an ערל do the פרה אדומה Parah adumah like a טבול יום?
Tvul yom? The basic answer had been yes, but we found a
ברייתא Braisa that said no. And we said that the ברייתא that
said no was the ברייתא of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva who said
that an ערל was like a טמא. Tamei. So again we have
a fascinating—Rava objected but we have a fascinating new understanding of—oops—of new
understanding of we have a fascinating new understanding of רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva in all areas, at least as
terms of personal status would be concerned, would say whatever a טמא
Tamei is invalid from, an ערל is invalid from. Okay.